(upbeat music)
- Hello, everyone.
Welcome to English Pod.
Today I'm here with Erica.
Hi, Marco.
- And I'm Marco.
(laughing)
- And we're bringing you a great elementary
lesson about a situation at an office.
- That's true.
Today we're gonna learn some
phrases for asking for time off.
- Right, asking for time off.
- Or asking for leave.
- Asking for leave, right.
- Right, so we're gonna
give you some great phrases
and vocabulary for when
you want to ask for leave.
So let's just listen to our dialogue today
where at an office where
live once some time off.
(upbeat music)
- Mr. McKenna, do you have a second?
I need to talk to you about something.
- Sure, live, what can I do for you?
- Well, I was just wondering,
you see, I know I've used up
all my vacation days this year
but my sister's getting married
and the wedding is over season, well.
You want to take some
time off, is that right?
- Well, sir, I was just hoping I might be
able to take some unpaid leave this year.
- What dates are you
planning on taking off?
I'll need at least two months notice
so that I can plan for your absence.
- I was thinking of taking off
from September 1st until the 30th.
Would you be okay with that?
- Well, I guess so.
(upbeat music)
- Well, it sounds like the boss
wasn't too happy about lives request.
- Well, she wanted to
take off for 30 days, so.
- I guess that is a long time.
- That is a long time,
I wish I could do that.
- Yeah, okay, we have
some great words for you
today so let's start with
our language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- Four words on our
language takeaway today.
Erica, why don't you tell us the first one?
- The first word is vacation days.
- Vacation days.
- So what are vacation days?
- Basically, it's the number
of personal leave days.
So the number of days that
you can take to go on vacation.
- How many vacation days do you have?
- Yeah, I think I have not so many.
I only have 10 vacation days.
- And vacation.
- Well, in some countries, there
are 10 vacation days is normal.
Another, I guess, it's 10,
15, even 20, I've heard.
- Yeah, yeah, well, vacation days.
- We can't take too many vacation days.
- There also we won't
make any more podcasts.
- Yeah.
- Why don't we look at
our second word, overseas.
- Overseas overseas.
When you travel overseas,
you travel over the ocean.
- Over the ocean to another country.
- Exactly.
- Okay, overseas.
Okay, and our third word for
language takeaway, unpaid leave.
Unpaid leave, unpaid leave.
So this is time off without pay.
- Simple, right, unpaid leave.
And our last word, notice,
notice, notice, notice.
- So we have some great
examples on how we use notice,
and from these
examples, I'm sure you'll be
able to understand
exactly what they mean.
- Example one.
- If you want to quit your job,
make sure you give enough notice.
You'll need to tell us
four weeks in advance.
- Example two.
- You didn't give me enough
notice about this project.
I didn't have enough time to finish it.
- So when you give someone notice,
you give them information in advance.
- In advance, right.
So if I want to take time off, I need to
give my boss, notice, advance information.
- Right, 15 day notice,
20 day notice, et cetera.
- Great, so that's our
language takeaway for today.
Now we are ready to listen
to our dialogue a second
time, and this time it's
gonna be really slow.
(upbeat music)
- Mr. McKenna, do you have a second?
- I need to talk to you about something.
- Sure, live, what can I do for you?
- Well, I was just wondering, you see,
I know I've used up all my
vacation days this year, but my sister
is getting married, and the
wedding is overseas, and, well...
- You wanna take some
time off, is that right?
- Well, sir, I was just
hoping that I might
be able to take some
unpaid leave this year.
- What dates are you
planning on taking off?
I'll need at least two months notice,
so that I can plan for your absence.
- I was thinking of taking off
from September 1st, until the 30th.
Would you be okay with that?
- I guess so.
(upbeat music)
- A lot of non-native
English speakers sometimes
feel quite nervous about
asking their boss for time off.
- Okay.
- Yeah, I guess it's a
kind of a difficult subject.
- Yeah, but today we're gonna
teach you some great phrases
that you can use next time you
need to ask for some time off.
- Great, so why don't we take
a look at putting it together?
- Putting it together.
- Okay, so I'm putting it together today.
We're gonna talk about some great phrases
that you can use when
approaching your boss.
- Yes, we heard Liv say this.
- Do you have a second?
- This is a nice way
to make sure your boss
isn't busy when you
wanna ask him something.
- Right, right, right, but we could
also say this in two different ways.
Let's listen.
- Do you have a minute?
I wanna ask you something.
- Do you have a sec?
I need to talk to you.
- A great way to approach your boss.
- Yeah, I love this
phrase, do you have a sec?
- Yeah, do you have a sec?
It's really natural.
Okay, so you've asked your boss for Liv
and you want to make
sure that he agrees with you.
- Yes, and this is how Liv did it.
- Would you be okay with that?
Would you be okay with that?
- This is a great pattern and we've got
two other examples of how you can use it.
- Example one.
- Are you all right with that?
- Example two.
- Will you be okay with this?
- Example three.
- I'm fine with that.
- Okay, great examples, great patterns.
Really useful language.
- Yes.
- Okay, so now let's listen
to our dialogue a third time.
- Mr. McKenna, do you have a second?
- I need to talk to you about something.
- Sure, Liv, what can I do for you?
- Well, I was just wondering, you see,
I know I've used up all my
vacation days this year but my
sister's getting married and
the wedding is overseas and well.
- You want to take some
time off, is that right?
- Well, sir, I was just hoping I might be
able to take some unpaid leave this year.
- What dates are you
planning on taking off?
I'll need at least two months notice
so that I can plan for your absence.
- I was thinking of taking off from
September 1st until the third year.
Would you be okay with that?
- Well, I guess so.
- I really noticed how Liv in this dialogue
used a lot of really polite language, how?
- Yeah, I guess when you're
talking to your boss, you really
have to be respectful and you
have to use really polite language.
What sort of things did she do
to make herself seem more polite?
- Well, she said a
couple of interesting
phrases for example,
well, I was just wondering.
- Yeah, I was just wondering, right?
I was like, well, she's kind of setting up
to ask for a favor or something.
- And she also used another
phrase that I thought was interesting.
- Yeah, she also said I was
just hoping that, yes, right?
I was just hoping that maybe
I could take some time off.
- Yeah, again, that sort of
doesn't sound too strong.
So it seems a bit more polite.
- Yeah, because if she said, well, I want
to take some time off, that's too strong.
- Yeah, so I was just hoping.
- And then, well, the boss says,
okay, well, when do you want to leave?
And she says, well, I
was thinking of, right?
I was thinking of,
yeah, again, if she would
have said, I want to,
yes, too strong, right?
- Yeah, in English,
sometimes we are careful
to not be too direct when
we're asking for something, right?
- Right, yeah.
- Because if you're too direct,
you sound a little bit impolite.
- Yeah, you sound rude, yeah.
- Okay, so great tips and
great things to take into
consideration the next time
you're talking into your boss.
- All right, guys, we're out of time,
but thanks for listening, and be sure
to check out our website, EnglishPod.
com, where you can
leave all your questions
and comments, and we'll
be there to answer them.
But I guess until then, it's goodbye.
(upbeat music)